<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->
<!ENTITY I-D.draft-sridharan-virtualization-nvgre SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-sridharan-virtualization-nvgre-05.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.vepc SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-matsushima-stateless-uplane-vepc-01.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.draft-ietf-idr-error-handling SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-idr-error-handling-13.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.draft-yamaya-ipsecme-mpsa SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-yamaya-ipsecme-mpsa-04.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.IPVPN-overlay SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-drao-bgp-l3vpn-virtual-network-overlays-03.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.EVPN-overlay SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-sd-l2vpn-evpn-overlay-03.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.draft-ietf-mpls-in-udp SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-mpls-in-udp-05.xml">
]>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="no"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="5"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>

<rfc category="std" docName="draft-vandevelde-idr-remote-next-hop-08"
     ipr="trust200902">

  <front>

    <title abbrev="">BGP Remote-Next-Hop</title>

    <author fullname="Gunter Van de Velde" initials="G."
            surname="Van de Velde">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>De Kleetlaan 6a</street>
          <city>Diegem</city>
          <country>Belgium</country>
          <code>1831</code>
        </postal>
        <phone>+32 2704 5473</phone>
        <email>gvandeve@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Keyur Patel" initials="K."
            surname="Patel">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 W. Tasman Drive</street>
          <city>San Jose, CA 95124</city>
          <country>USA</country>
          <code>95134</code>
        </postal>
        <phone></phone>
        <email>keyupate@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dhananjaya Rao" initials="D."
            surname="Rao">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 W. Tasman Drive</street>
          <city>San Jose, CA 95124</city>
          <country>USA</country>
          <code>95134</code>
        </postal>
        <phone></phone>
        <email>dhrao@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>


    <author fullname="Robert Raszuk" initials="R."
            surname="Raszuk">
      <organization>NTT MCL Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>101 S Ellsworth Avenue Suite 350</street>
          <city>San Mateo, CA  94401</city>
          <country>US</country>
          <code></code>
        </postal>
        <phone></phone>
        <email>robert@raszuk.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="R." surname="Bush" fullname="Randy Bush">
      <organization>Internet Initiative Japan</organization>
      <address>
	<postal>
	  <street>5147 Crystal Springs</street>
	  <city>Bainbridge Island</city>
	  <region>Washington</region>
	  <code>98110</code>
	  <country>US</country>
	  </postal>
	<email>randy@psg.com</email>
	</address>
      </author>

    <date month="September" year="2014" />

    <area>Routing</area>

    <workgroup>IDR</workgroup>

    <abstract>

      <t>The BGP Remote-Next-Hop attribute is an optional transitive attribute intended
        to facilitate automatic tunneling across an AS for an NLRI in a given address 
        family.  The attribute carries one or more tunnel end-points and 
        associated tunnel encapsulation information for a NLRI.  
       </t>

    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>

    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">

       <t><xref target="RFC5512"/> defines an attribute attached to an NLRI to signal 
         tunnel end-point encapsulation information between two BGP speakers for a
         single tunnel. <xref target="RFC5512"/> requires that a new address-family 
         needs to be enabled between the two BGP speakers.  It also assumes that the exchanged 
         tunnel endpoint is the NLRI.
       </t>

       <t>This document defines a new BGP transitive attribute known as a
         Remote-Next-Hop BGP attribute for Intra-AS and Inter-AS usage, and 
         simplifies the exchange and operations involved with tunnel end-point 
         information propagation between two BGP speakers.
       </t>

       <t>The tunnel endpoint information and the tunnel encapsulation
         information is carried within a Remote-Next-Hop BGP attribute.  This
         attribute can be added to any BGP NLRI.  This way the Address Family
         (AF) of the NLRI exchanged is decoupled from the tunnel SAFI address-
         family defined in <xref target="RFC5512"/>. Multiple Remote-Next-Hop 
         attribute TLVs can be added to a single NLRI.
       </t>

       <t>Security measures SHOULD be taken to protect against accidental or  
         malicious tampering of the Remote-Next-Hop attribute. 
       </t>


      </section>

     <section title="Requirements Language">
       <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
	 NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
	 "OPTIONAL" are to be interpreted as described in
	 <xref target="RFC2119"/> only when they appear in all upper
	 case.  They may also appear in lower or mixed case as English
	 words, without any normative meaning.</t>
     </section>

   <section title="Remote-Next-Hop Attribute">

       <t>There are an increasing number of use cases where the exchange of
	   multiple unique tunnel endpoints and associated tunnel data is 
	   desired for a prefix using segments of an existing infrastructure, where 
	   requiring a new address-family to be enabled would add operational complexity.
       </t>

       <t>The BGP Remote-Next-Hop attribute is defined to be attached to each
         originated BGP NLRI in any applicable address-family. Multiple
         Remote-Next-Hop attribute TLVs can be applied to a single originated BGP
         NLRI. Each TLV can contain one or more sub-TLVs that carry encapsulation
         information. Thus, it enables a simple mechanism to signal multiple,
         unique tunnel endpoints for a given prefix; as well as multiple
         encapsulation parameters for prefixes with the same remote tunnel end-point.
       </t>

       <t>BGP Remote-Next-Hop attribute is a Transitive Optional BGP attribute,
         allowing to signal next-hop encapsulation parameters in a transitive manner
         without the requirement to enable a new address-family.
       </t>
	   
	   <t>This document specifies the tunnel types that can be used with this 
	   attribute. The sub-TLVs from <xref target="RFC5512"/> and BGP IPsec tunnel encapsulation 
         <xref target="RFC5566"/> are reused for the BGP Next-Hop-Attribute. 
       </t>

	     <section title="Tunnel Encapsulation attribute versus BGP Remote-Next-Hop attribute ">
             <t>The use of Tunnel Encapsulation attribute <xref target="RFC5512"/> is based on the
             principle that the tunnel end-point is carried as part of BGP NLRI in
             an Encapsulation SAFI.
             </t>

             <t>This requires enabling of the Encapsulation SAFI within a BGP 
             enabled network. It also sets up an interdependency between BGP routes 
             in different SAFIs and the BGP Tunnel SAFI for resolving tunnel next-hops. 
             </t>

             <t>The Encapsulation SAFI <xref target="RFC5512"/> assumes that the tunnel endpoint is
             the NLRI exchanged in the Encaps SAFI, while Remote-Next-Hop decouples the exchanged
             NLRI from the tunnel end-point information, thereby requiring mutual
             exclusive usage of the two mechanisms.
             </t>

             <t>While <xref target="RFC5512"/> allows multiple tunnel endpoints and multiple tunnel
             types to be carried within a BGP Encaps SAFI, the correlation of
             Tunnel information with other SAFIs is done using the color extended
             community which is also non-trivial.
             </t>
         </section>
   </section>


   <section title=" BGP Remote-Next-Hop attribute TLV Format">

   <t>This attribute is an optional transitive attribute
     <xref target="RFC1771"/>.</t>

   <t>The BGP Remote-Next-Hop attribute is composed of a set of
     Type-Length-Value (TLV) encodings. The type code of the attribute
     is (IANA to assign). Each TLV contains information corresponding 
	 to a particular tunnel end-point address. 
   </t>

   <t>
   <figure>
      <artwork>
   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |   Tunnel Type (2 Octets)    |              Length             |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   | Addr len    |     Tunnel Address (IPv4 or IPv6)               |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                          AS Number                            |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                   Tunnel Parameters                           |
   ~                                                               ~
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+


   Tunnel Type (2 octets): identifies the type of tunneling technology
   being signaled.  This document specifies the following types:

   - L2TPv3 over IP [RFC3931]: Tunnel Type = 1
   - GRE [RFC2784]: Tunnel Type = 2
   - Transmit tunnel endpoint [RFC5566]: Tunnel Type = 3
   - IPsec in Tunnel-mode [RFC5566]: Tunnel Type = 4
   - IP in IP tunnel 
           with IPsec Transport Mode [RFC5566]: Tunnel Type = 5
   - MPLS-in-IP tunnel 
           with IPsec Transport Mode [RFC5566]: Tunnel Type = 6
   - IP in IP [RFC2003] [RFC4213]: Tunnel Type = 7

   This document defines the following types:
   - VXLAN: Tunnel Type = 8
   - NVGRE: Tunnel Type = 9
   - GTP: Tunnel Type = 10
   - MPLS-in-GRE: Tunnel Type = 11
   - MPLS-in-UDP: Tunnel Type = 12
   - MPLS-in-UDP-with-DTLS: Tunnel Type = 13

   Unknown types MUST be ignored and skipped upon receipt.

   Length (2 octets): the total number of octets of the value field.

   Tunnel Address Length - Addr len (1 octet): Length of Tunnel 
   Address. Set to 4 bytes for an IPv4 address and 16 bytes for an
   IPv6 address.

   AS Number - The AS number originating the BGP Remote-Next-Hop 
   attribute and is either a 2-byte AS or 4-Byte AS number

   Tunnel Parameter - (variable): comprised of multiple sub-TLVs.  
   Each sub-TLV consists of three fields: a 1-octet type, 1-octet 
   length, and zero or more octets of value.
      </artwork>
   </figure>
   </t>

   </section>

   <section title="Encapsulation sub-TLVs for virtual network overlays">

   <t>A VN-ID may need to be signaled along with the encapsulation types 
   for DC overlay encapsulations such as [VXLAN] and [NVGRE]. The VN-ID when 
   present in the encapsulation sub-TLV for an overlay encapsulation, MUST be 
   processed by a receiving device if it is capable of understanding it. The 
   details regarding how such a signaled VN-ID is processed and used is 
   defined in specifications such as [IPVPN-overlay] and [EVPN-overlay].
   </t>

   <section title="Encapsulation sub-TLV for VXLAN">
     <t>
       This document defines a new encapsulation sub-TLV format, defined in
       <xref target="RFC5512"></xref>, for VXLAN tunnels. When the tunnel type
       is VXLAN, the following is the structure of the value field in the
       encapsulation sub-TLV:
       </t>
     <t>
   <figure>
      <artwork>

   0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |V|M|R|R|R|R|R|R|          VN-ID (3 Octets)                   |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                 MAC Address (4 Octets)                      |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+   
    |  MAC Address (2 Octets)     |   Reserved                    |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+   


    V: When set to 1, it indicates that a valid VN-ID is present in the 
    encapsulation sub-TLV.
    M: When set to 1, it indicates that a valid MAC Address is present 
    in the encapsulation sub-TLV. 
    R: The remaining bits in the 8-bit flags field are reserved for 
    further use. They MUST be set to 0 on transmit and MUST be ignored 
    on receipt.

    VN-ID: Contains a 24-bit VN-ID value, if the 'V' flag bit is set.
    If the 'V' flag is not set, it SHOULD be set to zero and MUST be 
    ignored on receipt.

    The VN-ID value is filled in the VNI field in the VXLAN packet 
    header as defined in [VXLAN].

    MAC Address: Contains an Ethernet MAC address if the 'M' flag bit 
    is set. If the 'M' flag is not set, it SHOULD set to all zeroes and 
    MUST be ignored on receipt.

    The MAC address is local to the device advertising the route, and 
    should be included as the destination MAC address in the inner 
    Ethernet header immediately following the outer VXLAN header, in 
    the packets destined to the advertiser.
      </artwork>
   </figure>
     </t>
   </section>

   <section title="Encapsulation sub-TLV for NVGRE">
     <t>
       This document defines a new encapsulation sub-TLV format, defined in
       <xref target="RFC5512"></xref>, for NVGRE tunnels.  When the tunnel type
       is NVGRE, the following is the structure of the value field in the
       encapsulation sub-TLV:
     </t>

     <t>
   <figure>
      <artwork>

   0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |V|M|R|R|R|R|R|R|          VN-ID (3 Octets)                   |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                 MAC Address (4 Octets)                      |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+   
    |  MAC Address (2 Octets)     |   Reserved                    |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+   

    V: When set to 1, it indicates that a valid VN-ID is present in the 
    encapsulation sub-TLV.
    M: When set to 1, it indicates that a valid MAC Address is present 
    in the encapsulation sub-TLV. 
    R: The remaining bits in the 8-bit flags field are reserved for 
    further use. They MUST be set to 0 on transmit and MUST be ignored 
    on receipt.

    VN-ID: Contains a 24-bit VN-ID value, if the 'V' flag bit is set.
    If the 'V' flag is not set, it SHOULD be set to zero and MUST be 
    ignored on receipt.

    The VN-ID value is filled in the VSID field in the NVGRE packet 
    header as defined in [NVGRE].

    MAC Address: Contains an Ethernet MAC address if the 'M' flag bit is 
    set. If the 'M' flag is not set, it SHOULD set to all zeroes and 
    MUST be ignored on receipt.

    The MAC address is local to the device advertising the route, and 
    should be included as the destination MAC address in the inner 
    Ethernet header immediately following the outer NVGRE header, in 
    the packets destined to 
    the advertiser.

      </artwork>
   </figure>
     </t>
   </section>

<section title="Encapsulation sub-TLV for GTP">
     <t>
       This document defines a new encapsulation sub-TLV format, defined in
       <xref target="RFC5512"></xref>, for GTP tunnels. When the tunnel type
       is GTP, the following is the structure of the value field in the
       encapsulation sub-TLV:
       </t>
     <t>
   <figure>
      <artwork>

   0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                    Local TEID (4 Octets)                    |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
    |       Local Endpoint Address (4/16 Octets (IPv4/IPv6))      |
    .                                                             .
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 


    Local TEID: Contains a 32-bit Tunnel Endpoint Identifier of a 
    GTP tunnel assigned by EPC that is used to distinguish different
    connections in received packets within the tunnel.

    Local Endpoint Address: Indicates a 4-octets IPv4 address or 
    16-octets IPv6 address as a local endpoint address of GTP tunnel.

    Local Endpoint Address element makes a tunnel endpoint router 
    allow to have multiple Local TEID spaces. Received GTP packets 
    are identified which tunnel connection by combination of Local 
    Endpoint Address and Local TEID.
    
       </artwork>
   </figure>
     </t>
   </section>

<section title="Encapsulation for MPLS-in-GRE">
     <t>
       This document defines a new encapsulation sub-TLV format, defined in
       <xref target="RFC5512"></xref>, for MPLS-in-GRE tunnels. When the tunnel type
       is MPLS-in-GRE, the following is the structure of the value field in an optional
       encapsulation sub-TLV:
       </t>
     <t>
   <figure>
      <artwork>

   0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                     GRE-Key (4 Octets)                      |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 


    GRE-Key: 4-octet field [RFC2890] that is generated by the 
    advertising router.  The actual method by which the key is obtained
    is beyond the scope of this document.  The key is inserted into the
    GRE encapsulation header of the payload packets sent by ingress 
    routers to the advertising router.  It is intended to be used for 
    identifying extra context information about the received payload.
    Note that the key is optional. Unless a key value is being 
    advertised, the MPLS-in-GRE encapsulation sub-TLV MUST NOT be
	present.
	
	Note that signaling a GRE tunnel-type with routes in a labeled SAFI	
	may be sufficient to indicate to the receiver that it needs to send	
 	MPLS packets with that GRE encapsulation. However, a specific 
	tunnel-type for MPLS-in-GRE is being defined in order to make 
	this indication explicit to a receiver.
    </artwork>
   </figure>
     </t>
   </section>
   </section>

    <section title="Remote-Next-Hop Bestpath Considerations">

      <t>Traditionally a BGP speaker uses the IGP cost towards the BGP Next-
	     Hop as a BGP path selection criteria.  However, when a BGP speaker is
	     configured to use the BGP Remote-Next-Hop value, then it SHOULD use
		 the IGP cost towards the IP address selected from the Remote-Next-Hop
		 attribute. When there are multiple such IP addresses that may be
		 installed, it SHOULD use the worst IGP cost among them.
	  </t>
		 
	   <t>Similarly, the speaker SHOULD also check that the IP
		 address is reachable before considering that path eligible for
		 bestpath.
      </t>

   </section>

    <section title="Securing Remote-Next-Hop">

         <t>The Remote-Next-Hop attribute provides a set of tunnel parameters.
		 While the Remote-Next-Hop attribute has as goal to inform an intended 
		 recipient with these tunnel parameters, it is important to make sure 
		 that the attributes have not been tampered with and that they are 
		 restricted to the intended scope of distribution for secure operation. 
		 </t>

     <section title="Restrictions on Announcing of Remote-Next-Hop Attribute">

      <t>The Remote-Next-Hop attribute is used to carry an additional information 
        (tunnel end-point, encapsulation type, etc). It has a security value 
        to contain the distribution of the Remote-Next-Hop attribute within its
        planned scope of distribution. This scope could be, but is not limited 
        to, a particular department, site, organization, across ASes within a 
        same administration control or a global scope.
      </t>

      <t>To contain distribution of the Remote-Next-Hop attribute beyond its 
        intended scope of applicability, attribute filtering MAY be deployed. 
        The BGP speaker communicating to a speaker beyond the intended scope 
        of the Remote-Next-Hop attribute SHOULD filter the attribute during 
        the route announcements. 
      </t>

      <t>To facilitate attribute filtering, an implementation that supports 
        the BGP Remote-Next-Hop attribute MUST support a policy to (1) ignore 
        the received attribute and (2) filter the attribute.
      </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Restrictions on Originating of Remote-Next-Hop Attribute">

      <t>A BGP Remote-Next-Hop attribute may be added to routes that belong to 
        same Autonomous system as the tunnel endpoint address. Implementations 
        should validate the following to ensure the validity of Remote-Next-Hop Attribute:
      </t>

        <t>(1) BGP Remote-Next-Hops Tunnel Endpoint and AS number association using BGP
          Origin Validation.
        </t>

        <t>(2) BGP Remote-Next-Hop Tunnel Endpoints underlay routes origin AS MUST 
          be same as the AS number carried within BGP Remote-Next-Hop attribute.
        </t>

        <t>(3) The origin AS of BGP Routes that carry BGP Remote-Next-Hop
		attribute MUST be same as the AS number carried within BGP 
		Remote-Next-Hop attribute.
		</t>
		
		<t>(4) A BGP speaker that advertises its received routes to peers with its local
		  address as the BGP next-hop may add the Remote-Next-Hop attribute to
		  the routes if it desires to signal a tunnel encapsulation for its
		  peers to use while sending traffic to the speaker for those routes.
		</t>


   </section>
   </section>

      <section title="Multiple tunnel endpoint addresses">

      <t>In some cases, a device may need to accept incoming traffic for a	
 	   prefix via multiple different encapsulations, to support interactions	
 	   with remote devices with disjoint capabilities. Certain device	
 	   implementations cannot support the use of the same IP address as	
 	   local tunnel endpoint for multiple encapsulations.
      </t>
	  
 	  <t>	
 	   In certain cases, a device may need to signal an additional,	
 	   alternate tunnel endpoint address, to be used by other devices only	
 	   as a backup in certain failure conditions.
	  </t>


   </section>
   
    <section title="Attribute error handling">

      <t>When receiving a BGP Update message containing a malformed Remote-Next-Hop 
        attribute, the attribute MUST be quietly ignored and not passed along to 
        other BGP peers. (see [draft-ietf-idr-error-handling], Section 7).  This is equivalent to the 
        -attribute discard- action specified in [draft-ietf-idr-error-handling].
      </t>

      <t>Note that a BGP Remote-Next-Hop attribute MUST NOT be considered to 
        be malformed because it contains more than one TLV of a given type 
        or because it contains TLVs of unknown types.
      </t>

      <t>If a BGP path attribute is received that has the Remote-Next-Hop 
        attribute codepoint but does not have the transitive bit set, the 
        attribute MUST be considered to be a malformed Remote-Next-Hop 
        attribute and MUST be discarded as specified in this section.
      </t>

   </section>

    <section title="BGP speakers that do not support BGP Remote-Next-Hop attribute">

      <t>If a device does not support this attribute, and receives this
	    attribute, then it follows the normal NLRI processing and BGP best
		path selection, and the resulting forwarding decision is used, as the
		attribute is optional.
      </t>

   </section>

    <section title="Use Case scenarios">
      <t>This section provides a brief overview of some use-cases for the BGP
	    Remote-Next-Hop attribute.  Use of the BGP Remote-Next-Hop is not
		limited to the examples in this section. Details regarding how the
		attribute is used are described in the respective solution drafts
		that are referenced where necessary.
      </t>

      <section title="Stateless user-plane architecture for virtualized EPC (vEPC)">
      <t>The full usage case of BGP Remote-Next-Hop regarding vEPC can be 
        found in [vEPC], while [RFC6459] documents IPv6 in 3GPP EPS.
      </t>
	
      <t>3GPP introduces Evolved Packet Core (EPC) that is fully IP based
        mobile system for LTE and -advanced in their Release-8 specification
        and beyond.  Operators are now deploying EPC for LTE services and
        encounter rapid LTE traffic growth.  There are various activities to
        offload mobile traffic in 3GPP and IETF such as LIPA, SIPTO and DMM.
        The concept is similar that traffic of OTT (Over The Top) application
        is offloaded at entity that is closer to the mobile node (ex. eNodeB
        or closer anchor).
       </t>

        </section>



      <section title="Stateless User-plane Architecture for virtual Packet Edge">

	<t>With the emergence of the NfV technologies, different architectures are 
         proposed for virtualized services. These functions will normally run in the datacenter.
         
         BGP remote-next-hop can be used to inject traffic into the virtualized services 
         running in the datacenter using tunnels. These tunnels can be signalled using BGP remote-next-hop. 
         This facilitates a dynamic, simple and clean routing architecture.
         BGP Remote Next Hop can simplify the orchestration or provisioning layer by signalling the 
         tunnel endpoint (virtual provider edge router) in combination with the encapsulation protocol. 
        </t>

         <t>If this is used together with orchestrated traffic steering mechanisms 
         (i.e. BGP Flowspec) , it is possible to differentiate at application level, and forward 
         each different traffic types towards the desired destination.
	</t>

       </section>


      <section title="Dynamic Network Overlay Infrastructure">

	<t>The BGP Remote-Next-Hop extension allows consistent signalling of
	  tunnel encapsulations as needed by virtual network overlay solutions
	  such as <xref target="I-D.drao-bgp-l3vpn-virtual-network-overlays"/> and <xref target="I-D.sd-l2vpn-evpn-overlay"/>
	</t>
       </section>

      <section title="Simple VPN solution using Multi-point Security Association">
	<t>[draft-yamaya-ipsecme-mpsa] describes the overlay network solution by utilizing 
          dynamically established IPsec multi-point Security Association (SA) without 
          individual connection.
        </t>

        <t>Multi-point SA technology provides the simplified mechanism of the
          Auto Discovery and Configuration function.  This is applicable for
          any IPsec tunnels such as IPv4 over IPv4, IPv4 over IPv6, IPv6 over
          IPv4 and IPv6 over IPv6.
        </t>

        <t>MPSA does not provide peer discovery function by itself. However,
          other mechanism, such as BGP, can be employed with MPSA for
          automatic peer discovery. BGP Remote-Next-Hop can be used to learn 
          peer information as next-hops.
       </t>
       </section>

    </section>

    <section title="BGP Remote-Next-Hop Community">

       <t>This document defines a new BGP Extended Community 
          called "BGP Remote-Next-Hop Extended Community".
       </t>
     
       <t>The BGP Remote-Next-Hop extended community is transitive 
	  across AS boundaries [RFC4360]
       </t>
	
       <t>The Global Administrator field of this Community MUST be 
          set to the ASN of the PE originating this community. 
          The Local Administrator field of this Community MUST 
	  be set to 0.
        </t>
	 
	 <t>The Remote-Next-Hop extended community SHOULD be 
	   attached to those BGP routes which are used to resolve 
	   the Tunnel endpoints carried in BGP Remote-Next-Hop attribute.
	 </t>

    </section>

  <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">

      <t>This document defines a new BGP attribute known as a BGP Remote-Next-
        Hop attribute.  We request IANA to allocate a new attribute code from
        the -BGP Path Attributes- registry with a symbolic name -Remote-Next-
        Hop- attribute.
      </t>

      <t>We also request IANA to allocate four new BGP Tunnel Types from the
        -BGP Tunnel Encapsulation Attribute Tunnel Types- registry with the
        following symbolic names: -VXLAN- with Tunnel type 8, -NVGRE- with
        Tunnel type 9, -GTP- with Tunnel type 10, -MPLS-in-GRE with
        Tunnel type 11, -MPLS-in-UDP- with Tunnel type 12 and 
		-MPLS-in-UDP-with-DTLS with Tunnel type 13.
      </t>

  </section>

  <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
    <t>This technology could be used as technology as man in the middle
       attack, however with existing RPKI validation for BGP that risk
       is reduced.</t>

    <t>The distribution of Tunnel end-point address information can
       result in potential DoS attacks. Therefore is it strongly recommended to
       install traffic filters, IDSs and IPSs at the perimeter of the
       tunneled network infrastructure.
    </t>

    <t>measures SHOULD be taken to protect the validity of the BGP 
       Remote-Next-Hop attribute. It is possible to inject a rogue 
       BGP Remote-Next-Hop attribute to an NLRI resulting in Monkey-In-The-Middle 
       attack (MITM).  To avoid this type of MITM attack, it is strongly recommended to
	  use a technology mechanism to verify that for NLRI it is the
	  expected BGP Remote-Next-Hop. We anticipate that this can be
	  done with an expansion of RPKI-Based origin validation, see
	  <xref target="I-D.ietf-sidr-pfx-validate"/>.
       </t>

       <t>This does not avoid the fact that rogue AS numbers may be
	  inserted or injected into the AS-Path. To achieve protection
	  against that threat BGP Path Validation should be used, see
	  <xref target="I-D.ietf-sidr-bgpsec-overview"/>.
       </t>


  </section>

    <section anchor="Privacy" title="Privacy Considerations">
      <t>This proposal may introduce privacy issues, however with BGP 
	 security mechanisms in place they should be prevented.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors would like to thanks Satoru Matsushima, Ryuji Wakikawa and Miya Kohno for their      
      usefull vEPC discussions. Istvan Kakonyi provided insight in the vPE use case scenario.</t>

      <t>Satoshi Usui provided datapoints around Simple VPN solution using Multi-point Security Association.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="log" title="Change Log">
      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Initial Version:">16 May 2012</t>
	  <t hangText="Hacked for -01:">17 July 2012</t>
	  <t hangText="Hacked for -05:">07 January 2014</t>
	  <t hangText="Hacked for -07:">15 September 2014</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1771"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2784" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3484" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3931" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4213" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4271" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5512" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5566" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6459" ?>
	  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7348" ?>
	 <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-mpls-in-udp"?>
	  </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
    <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-sidr-bgpsec-overview"?>
    <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-sidr-pfx-validate"?>
      &I-D.draft-sridharan-virtualization-nvgre;
      &I-D.vepc;
      &I-D.draft-ietf-idr-error-handling;
      &I-D.draft-yamaya-ipsecme-mpsa;
	  &I-D.IPVPN-overlay;
	  &I-D.EVPN-overlay;

	  

    </references>

  </back>

</rfc>
